虚刀流七代目当主
The 7th Kyotouryuu head, Yasuri Shichika.
鑢七花
The army general director in support of critical tasks under direct control of Yanari Shogun of the Owari Shogunate,
尾張幕府家鳴将軍直轄預かり奉る所軍所総監督
Togame the Strategian.
奇策士とがめ
These two have begun their journey to collect Shikizaki Kiki's perfected Deviant Blades.
四季崎記紀の完成形変体刀を追う
二人の旅が始まりました
天下のすべるほどの力を持つと言われるその十二本の刀
It is said those who wield those 12 swords can rule the world.
After obtaining Zettou Kanna, previously held by Maniwa Koumori,
真庭蝙蝠が所持していた絶刀鉋を手に入れた二人は
旅支度のために
they have arrived at the city of Kyoto to prepare for the journey.
まず　今日の町を訪れたのでございます
Are you shocked at such an unfamiliar sight?
見慣れない光景に驚いたか
Yeah, there's people everywhere...
ああ　人間だらけだな
With this many, I really can't tell anyone apart.
こんなに多いと区別できない
There's no need to tell them apart or anything.
区別などせんでもよい
Really?
そうなのか
Yes.
そうだ
If you try to study every person that crosses your way, you'll go crazy in no time.
一々目に付く人間をすべて気にしていたら
頭が変になるぞ
I feel like I've gone crazy already, Togame.
俺はすでにおかしくなりそうだよ
とがめ
こら　私はこっちだ
Hey, I'm over here!
おお 同じような背丈だといよいよ分からん
I can't tell you apart from others due to your height...
酷いにもほどがあるな
How bad can you get...
Um...
あの
何
What?
Aren't you cold?
あなた寒くないんですか
いや
No?
ああ　こいつのことは気にするな
Don't mind him.
Think of him as a bear or some other animal.
熊か何かの仲間だと思ってくれ
O-Okay...
なんか変なのか
Is something weird?
If you ask me that, I'd have to say everything about you...
何が変と言えば
そなたの何もかもがと言わなければならないが
確かにそんな格好ではな
With that outfit you do look a bit...
どれもいやだ
I don't like any of them.
Staring a gift horse in the mouth, huh...
人の好意を無にするやつだな
I don't need anything like this to begin with.
そもそもこんなものは俺に必要ない
It'll make it hard to move.
動きにくくなる
People were looking at you as if you were naked back there.
それ以前に裸だと
さっきのような奇異な目で見られるのだ
I don't really care.
俺は別にかまわん
It's a problem for me.
私が困る
Walking along with a young, naked man in the depths of winter?
冬の寒空の下に
裸の若い男を連れ歩く
What would people think of a woman like that?
そんな女を人はどう思うだろうか
どう思うんだ
What would they think?
They'd see me as some dominatrix and harass me anywhere I go by throwing rocks as we pass.
異常な性癖の持ち主として
私は行く先々で迫害を受け
石粒をぶっつけられるだろうな
That'd be a problem.
それは困るな
If you agree then go find some clothes.
そう思うなら着物を着ろ
Living on the mainland comes with a lot of hassles...
本土ってのは色々面倒なんだな
And yet everyone lives through them.
そういう柵の中で皆生きておる
Have you decided what you'd like?
お決まりに成られましたか
Yes.
うむ　これとこれとそれとあれとあれをくれ
I'll take this and this and that and that and that please.
Wow, that many?
わー　そんなに
I don't need that many.
俺はそんなに要らないぞ
They're for me!
私のだ
Don't you already have a lot of clothes?
あんた服だったらもうたくさん着ているだろう
Learn to appreciate a lady's fashion sense.
女子のお洒落心を分かれ
I don't get it at all...
わかんねえなあ
You're the one I don't get.
分からんのはそなただ
What's with that getup?
何だ　その着こなしは
裸じゃないからいいだろう
I'm not naked so it's fine, isn't it?
I suppose it qualifies as original, and you could say it's chic to flaunt such a weather-defying outfit,
斬新といえば斬新で
この冬一番の挑戦的なお洒落といえるかも知れんが
あたしは好きではないなあ
but I'm not a fan of it.
I really don't get this whole like and dislike stuff.
好きとか嫌いとか
それこそよく分からねえ
何
What?
Yeah, sometimes you run into people like this.
ああ　こういう輩が偶にいるのだ
どうすればいい
What do I do?
Protect me.
私を守れ
了解
Understood.
I will protect you.
俺はあんたを守ろう
My, what pretty clothes you're wearing.
きれいなおべべをきっちゃってなあ
If you don't wanna die, you know what to do.
死にたくなければどうすればいいか分かるよなあ
I have no intention of handing anything over.
私は何も渡す気はないぞ
Also, if you guys don't want to die, keep your swords sheathed.
それにお前たち死にたくなかったら
刀は抜くな
何言って
What the hell are you—
だから刀を抜くなと
That's why I told you to keep them sheathed.
野郎
Damn you!
You guys would be dead if you were a little better at using those swords.
剣筋がもう少し増しだったら　お前たち死んでいたぞ
Kyotouryuu hidden art...
虚刀流奥義
Wait, wait!
待って待って
Why are you finishing them off?
なに止めを刺そうとしておるのだ
I can't?
しては駄目なのか
You can't!
しては駄目だ
Is that a mainland custom?
それも本土の仕来りか
It's common sense!
人間としての常識だ
They may be bad guys, but that doesn't mean you can just slaughter them.
悪人と言えと
問答無用に皆殺しにしてよいと言うわけではない
よかったな
You're lucky.
私が止めなければ本当に殺されていたぞ
If I hadn't stopped him you really would have died.
What a hassle...
面倒だ
A man who knows no one, a woman who closed her heart.
人を知らぬ男と心をなくした女
Thus their journey of hardship began.
前途多難な旅の幕開けてした
Zantou
Namakura
It's been a month since they started their search for Shikizaki Kiki's Deviant Blades.
四季崎記紀の変体刀を求める旅も
あれから一ヶ月
二本目の刀を求め
Togame and Shichika have headed to Inaba to find the second sword.
とがめと七花は
因幡を目指しておりました
Don't be so rough!
あまり強くするな
加減が分からん
I don't know how to hold back.
なあ　これまだ続けなきゃならないのか
Hey, do we have to keep doing this?
Until you're able to recognize me clearly.
そなたが私をしっかと認識できるようになるまでだ
いつまでも他人の判別がつかないびっくり人間のままでは困る
It'll be troublesome if you don't learn to distinguish people.
確かに
That's true.
茶目気で声をかけた際に
I just don't want to be mistaken for an assassin and killed if I call out to you as a joke.
刺客と間違えれて殺されて叶わんからな
それはそうだ
That's true.
だからこうして俺はしっかとお前の色や匂いを覚えようとしている
That's why I'm trying to learn your exact color and scent right now.
Idiot, you're not allowed to bite, okay?
ばか　噛むのは無しだぞ
噛んだら痛むからな
You'll injure me if you do.
How about licking?
舐めるのは
You're allowed to lick.
舐めるのはいい
Actually, go ahead and lick me to remember my taste.
むしろ舐めて味も覚えておけ
けれど　あんまり身をよじるな
Stop squirming around though.
頭皮が引っ張られるのは痛い
When you pull on my hair it hurts.
そうりゃそうだ
I guess.
教育とは滑稽なものだ
Training is a funny thing...
それはともかく
At any rate, we'll be in Inaba tomorrow.
明日は因幡だ
Oh, that...
おお　因幡の　ええと
何だっけ
What's it called again?
Gekoku Castle.
下酷城
収集対象は斬刀鈍だ
We're aiming for Zantou Namakura.
Note: Blunt, the Decapitator
弱そうな名前だなあ
That's a pretty weak-sounding name...
それは四季崎なりの皮肉だ
That's Shikizaki's sense of irony.
この斬刀は比類なき切れ味が特性だ
The main feature of Zantou is its unparalleled sharpness.
どんなものでも
It'll supposedly cut through absolutely anything effortlessly.
抵抗なく一刀両断してしまうらしいぞ
そうすると
So wait, what would happen if you tried to use Zantou to cut that tough Zettou?
その斬刀で頑丈な絶刀を斬ろうとした場合　どうなるんだ
試してみんと分からんが
I can't say for sure without trying,
but probably, the one that is less complete would yield.
おそらくは完成度の低いほうが矛盾なく負けることになるのだろう
作られたのは斬刀のほうが後になるはずだから
I think Zantou was made later, so if it came down to it, Zettou would probably be cut.
絶刀が斬られるのかもしれん
二本目に鈍を選んだのには理由がある
There's a reason I chose to go after Namakura next.
Our opponent this time is a swordsman.
今回の相手は剣士だ
A swordsman would be an easier opponent than a ninja.
剣士ならば忍者よりもやりやすい
He's a ronin named Uneri Ginkaku.
Note: Masterless samurai
宇練銀閣という浪人ということになるのかな
Or maybe you could call him a castle lord.
それともあるいは城主なのか
Long ago, when Shogun Kyuu ordered the sword hunt,
かつて、旧将軍が刀借り令を出した段階での所有者は
鳥取藩主に仕えた武士　宇練金閣
its owner was a samurai serving the Tottori feudal lord named Uneri Kinkaku.
武士としてあるまじきことだが
But in an act unbefitting of a samurai, Kinkaku refused to turn over Zantou.
金閣は斬刀の提出を拒んだ
"It belongs to me" he said.
飽くまでも　「我のものなり」と
その際　斬刀で撃退した旧将軍で兵団は
After that, he used Zantou to repulse the army Shogun Kyuu sent after him, killing over 10,000 soldiers.
合わせて一万を超えたという
10,000?!
一万
現所有者　宇練銀閣は十代目の子孫にあたると聞いている
Its current owner, Uneri Ginkaku, is supposedly his 10th generation descendant.
よどけた話いしがずはものてるいはらかますふ々堂とが者忍
忍者が堂々とふすまから入るってのもはずかしい話だけどよ
To enter through the front door, embarrassing it is, but,
かえねたかしはいあばのこ　あま
まあ　この場合は仕方ねえか
helped, it cannot be.
ぜうらもてせらのな　だぎさらしわにま
真庭白鷺だ　名乗らせてもらうぜ
Introduce myself, I shall.
Maniwa Shirasagi am I, one of the 12 heads of the Maniwa Corps.
りとひがうよりうとにうゆじんぐんにわにまはれお
俺は真庭忍軍十二頭領が一人
などけだんーつっぎさらしのりべやしさかさうよしうつ
通称「逆さ喋りの白鷺つーんだけどな」
"Reverse-talk Shirasagi" called I am.
鈍刀斬なたかいしろそっおのみ込れ触いといなはのもいなきで断両刀一
一刀両断できないものはないという触れ込みのおっそろしい刀斬刀鈍
Zantou Namakura, a fearsome sword heralded as able to slice through anything; take it I shall.
よれく　れそ
それ　くれよ
かえねやじうまちっなくしびさ
寂しくなっちまうじゃねえか
Don't ignore me, or lonely I will be.
よえねやじんすとかし　いおいお
おいおい　しかとすんじゃねえよ
かのいたみをうぽんにのれおになんそ　たんあもとれそ
それともあんた　そんなに俺の忍法をみたいのか
Or that much do you desire to see it?
ぜだんえねやじんもるれみになんそはし探鱗逆法忍の鷺白庭真
真庭白鷺の忍法逆鱗探しはそんなに見れるもんじゃねえんだぜ
Not to everyone my ninja arts do I show.
Now come on.
えねたっいま
参ったねえ
Are you trying to tell me that your "reverse talk" ninja art allows you to keep jabbering on after being sliced in half?
ひょっとして　あんたの忍法逆鱗探しとは
一刀両断されてもなお喋り続けることができるという技なのか
Woah!
わあーい いつの間に　銀 銀閣
Wh-When did you-
G-Ginkaku!
秘剣 零閃
Hiken: Zerosen.
ああ 畳が汚れちまったな
I got the tatami mats dirty...
実は俺親父に聞いていてさ
Actually, I heard about this place from my dad.
I've secretly been looking forward to it.
密かに楽しみにしていたんだが
Ah, Inaba today is no longer like what you've heard.
ああ そなたが聞いていた因幡の風景は以前のものだ
The Inaba desert started rapidly expanding about 5 years ago.
因幡砂漠は五年ほど前から拡大の一途を辿ってな
鳥取藩全土を呑み込んだ
It's since swallowed up the whole Tottori domain.
今や因幡は人の住めぬ地だ
Today, it's an uninhabitable land.
その宇練銀閣ってのはこんなところで何をやってるんだ
So what's that Uneri Ginkaku guy doing in a place like this?
I told you, he's the lord of a castle.
言ったであろう　城主であると
そいつが分からねえ
I don't get it.
こんな人の住めないところで殿様をやっていても仕方がないだろうに
Isn't it pointless being a feudal lord in a land where no one lives?
そう思って幕府からの遣いの者が何度も訪ねたのだがな
You'd think so, but of all the servants the Shogunate has sent there to scout it out,
誰一人として戻らなかった
not a single one has returned.
Cut first, ask later...
切り捨てごめんね
四季崎の刀の毒にやられておるのか
He might have been lured by the poison of Shikizaki's sword,
はたまた別に理由があるのか
or he might have some other reason.
So basically you have no clue?
何も分かっていないってこと
あんた頭脳労働専門だって言ってたよな
Didn't you say you specialize in brain work?
あれもこれも奇策のうちだ　そなたは詮索せんでもよい
Anything and everything I do is part of my plan.
You needn't bother asking.
ああ　そうだ　それはそれとしてそろそろ口癖を考えなければなあ
Ah, that's right!
That aside, you need to come up with a catchphrase.
はあ 口癖
A catchphrase?
そうだ
Right.
誰の
Whose?
そなたのだ
Yours.
I went ahead and wrote about your successful venture last month.
先月のなあ　そなたの活躍ぶりをとりあえず文字にしてみたのだ
ああ　報告書って奴な
Ah, that report thing?
そうそう　あんたの言うとおり
That's right, like you asked, I took down that ninja guy in a flashy way.
俺はあの忍者野郎を派手に遣っ付けたんだ
それなのだが
True as that is, I didn't actually see how flashy it was, so I couldn't write about it.
そなたがどれほど派手に真庭を遣っ付けたのかは
直に見たわけではないから　書けなかった
は　せっかくあんたの言うとおりにしたってんのに
I went out of the way to do as you asked too...
仕方なかろうが
I can't do anything about that.
I can't write about what I didn't see.
見ていないものは書きようがない
しかしまあ　それはあまり大した問題ではない
Though, it isn't really a huge problem, since you'll have more opportunities in the future.
また機会もあるだろうしな
それよりも　七花
More importantly Shichika, when I was writing about how we obtained Kanna, I noticed one important thing.
鉋収集の模様を書いているうちに
私は一つ大事なことに気づいたのだ
へえ　大事なことって
Important thing?
You have a weak personality!
そなたは個性が弱い
...is how I figure I should react, but what's the problem, exactly?
と流れのまま一応驚いてみたが
それが何の問題だ
So naive!
甘いぞ　素人か
Are you an amateur?
剣法以外は素人だよ
At everything but the sword arts.
You can't afford to be so selfish from now on.
そういう自分本位では治ることいかんな
What?
どうも報告書を書いていると
No matter how I worded the report, that Maniwa Koumori ninja stood out more than you.
そなたよりもあの忍者　真庭蝙蝠のほうが目立ってしまうのだ
推敲しても推敲しても結果は同じだ
I rewrote it and rewrote it but the result was the same.
ついぞ蝙蝠よりもそなたを目立たせることはできなかったのだ
I just couldn't make you stand out more than Koumori.
Wait a second...
いや　ちょっと待って
When I finished the final revision and read it over,
最終的に清書上で自分で読み返してみても
そなたのことは上半身裸のバかという印象しか残らなかった
no matter what, the only impression I got of you was that of a half-naked idiot.
I said wait a second, Togame-san!
だから待ってよ　とがめさん
あんなよ
Of course I'd lose in character to a guy who pulls swords from his mouth!
口から刀を取り出すような奴は相手に
個性で勝てるわけがないだろうが
戦闘では俺の勝ちだったんだからかまわないだろう
But I won the fight, so there shouldn't be any problem, right?
Of course, if you lose in fighting it'd be a problem, but it's also a problem if you lose in character.
それはもちろん戦闘で負けてもらっては困るが
個性でも負けてもらっては困る
そなたの人間性にはいまいち花がないのだ
Your personality has almost nothing interesting about it!
You don't hold back, do you?
あんたに気遣いはねのか
If I did, would I be able to write a captivating report?
気遣いで読者を取り込みするような報告書が書けるか
Just what kind of battle is she fighting?
こいつはいったい何と戦っているのだろう
たとえば蝙蝠に限らず　もっと強い個性を持つ忍びもいるのだぞ
Incidentally, there are other ninja with far stronger personalities than Koumori, you know?
Just among the ones I know, let's see...
私が知っている中でも
そうだな　逆さ喋りの白鷺という忍者がいて
There's a ninja called Shirasagi who speaks backwards.
そいつはなんと常に逆さ向きに喋るのだ
No matter what, he'll speak with his words reversed.
それにどういう意味があるんだ
What's the point of that?
没個性にならぬよう一生懸命なのだ
He's trying his utmost not to be boring.
忍者でそんなことも考えなくちゃならないのか　庭庭にって奴は
Do ninja have to take that into consideration too?
Those "Maniwani" guys...
Maniwani?
庭庭に
ああ　略したのか
Ah, you shortened it.
"Maniwa corps" is kind of hard to say.
真庭忍軍なんて言いにくいからなあ
I'll bite my tongue on it eventually.
いつか舌を噛んじまう
庭庭にか
Maniwani...
変か
Is it weird?
いいな　それ　可愛いぞ　採用だ
It's good.
Kind of cute. I approve.
そうか
I see.
Good job.
でかしたぞ 初めて冴えたことを言えたな　うむうむ
That's the first intelligent thing you've said.
Excellent.
The readers will get to know you and come to understand your outlook.
読者が親しみを思ってより世界観に引き込まれる
Your report sounds like a lot of work...
あんたの報告書って　大変なんだな
やっと分かったか
Finally understand, do you?
Well, it's true our opponents are extremely eccentric,
まあ　確かにあそこの連中は個性の塊みたいな者だから
目指せというのも
so asking you to try to reach their level is probably too much.
最終的にあそこまでたどり着けというのも酷な話だ
しかし七花　そうは言っても最低限の努力はしてもらわねばならぬ
Even so Shichika,
having said that, you still have to put in a minimum amount of effort.
そういうわけで　差し当たってそなたの口癖を考えようというのだ
That said, for the time being we'll focus on your catchphrase.
Is that really something you decide by thinking about it?
考えて決めるようなことなのか　それ
Yeah, it has to give the reader a kind of "wow, this guy isn't normal" impression.
ああ　こいつは普通じゃないんだなあと読者への印象が強くなる
I don't really mind if they think I'm normal...
俺は別に普通と思われてもいいんだけど
わたしがそうはいかん
I can't have that.
退屈で途中で読むのを止められてしまったらどうするのだ
What will happen if they get so bored they stop reading?
Does a report have to be that interesting?
報告書っておもしろく書かなくちゃならないのか
Oh yeah!
おおそうだ　例の天才剣士錆白兵の口癖もまあまあ格好良かったぞ
The genius swordsman Sabi Hakuhei's catchphrase is quite good.
私を裏切った奴のことを褒めるのも癪に障るが
As annoying as it is to speak well of someone who betrayed me,
それでも認めるべきところは認めねばなるまい
even so, I must give recognition where recognition is due.
参考までに聞こうか
I'll ask what it is just for reference.
"I'll have you fall for me."
「拙者にときめいてもらうでござる」
I'd die if I had a catchphrase like that...
そんな口癖をつけられたら悲惨だ
あそうだ　ほら　俺がよく口にする言葉があったぜ
Oh yeah!
There is something I'm always saying!
Oh?
ほお
You know, that "Such a hassle!" thing.
あのな　「面倒だ」ってやつ
「チェリオ」
Cheerio!
愚か者　そんなダルそうな言葉は個性として確立してどうする
You idiot, what kind of apathetic phrase is that to set up your character with?
Think about what it's like for me to write about such a stagnant character.
そんな動きのない登場人物を書く私の身にもなってみろう
途中で書くのをやめたくなってしまったらどうするのだ
What happens if I lose my will to write halfway through?
そうか
I see...
In the first place, if I described you constantly saying "it's a hassle it's a hassle!" while we're collecting swords,
そもそも刀を集めながら
「面倒だ　面倒だ」と言っている姿を描写したりしたら
まるでそなたがいやいや働いているようではないか
you'd come across as doing it unwillingly.
So I should work enthusiastically?
のりのりで働けってか
Exactly.
そのとおりだ
とにかく
Anyway, I just want to avoid looking like I forced you to do this.
私がそなたを無理やり働かしているかのような形になることだけは
避けたい
あんたこそ自分本位だろう
Pretty self-centered, aren't you...
とは言ってもなあ　そんな簡単に思いつかねえよ
Though that said, I can't just come up with something on the spot.
Don't worry.
安心しろ
そういうと思って私が予め考えておいてやった
I figured you'd say that, so I came up with some in advance.
まあ　そなたにも好みがあるだろうからなあ
Well I'm sure you'll like at least one.
候補の中から採集的に選ぶのはそなたの権利だ
You'll have the privilege of picking out the final candidate.
好きなものを選んでくれてかまわぬ
Pick whatever you like.
押し付けがましい権利だな
That's a pretty intrusive privilege...
まあ　好きなのがあったらな
Well, assuming I like any.
ふむ　案ずるな
Of course.
Don't worry, I've prepared some really cool catchphrases.
格好いい中でもお勧めの口癖を用意した
Hey,
the gods
love no one more
than me, yeah ?
「ほら　俺って誰よりも神から愛されてるじゃん」
"Hey, the gods loves no one more than me, yeah?"
ほ　ほら
"H-Hey"...
いや　確かあんたは戦闘能力を持たない代わりに
Didn't you say that you had brain power to make up for your lack of fighting prowess?
その分頭がいいって設定じゃなっかたっけ
What do you mean?
何を言う
A dumb person couldn't come up with that catchphrase.
こんな口癖　頭がよくなければ閃かんぞ
確かに悪魔的な閃きではあるが
It's true it has a certain evil ring to it...
基本的に敵に対して挑発の用途で使う言葉だな
Fundamentally, a catchphrase is meant to provoke your opponent.
格の違いを示すと言うか
Like pointing out the difference in status, or expressing your complete self-confidence.
自らの絶対的自信を示すと言うか
こういうセリフを言うことで
If you announce your omnipotence beforehand, when you win, it'll look like an easy victory.
そなたの全能性が現れると同時に
勝利を収めたときに　かなりの楽勝感が出る
ただのいやな奴になってる気がするぞ
It feels like I'd just become another bad guy...
ぶっちゃけ　そなたが多少いやな奴のほうが
Frankly, it'd help me out if you were a little more of a bad guy.
私としては助かるのだ
If I demonstrated the ability to handle a tough nut or a rowdy smart ass, my own standing would improve.
手に負えないようなやんちゃで生意気な荒くれ者を
手綱をとってうまく操ってこそ
私の評価も上がるだろうからな
その意味では　そなたは少し善良すぎる
In that respect, you're a little too nice.
勝手だ
So selfish...
「どうやらあんた島流しにされたいようだな」
Apparently you're looking to get exiled.
なぜ二十年もの間島流しに目にあっていた自分が
Why would a guy who was exiled for 20 years himself say that so proudly to someone else?
外の誰かに向けてそんな台詞を得意げに言わなければならないのだろう
Idiot.
ばか者　だからこそ説得力があってよいのだろう
That's exactly why it sounds so convincing.
I really don't need that...
要らねえよ　そんな説得力
好みのうるさい男だ
Such a picky guy...
この不毛な会話道中ずっと続くのだろうか
Does she intend to continue this pointless conversation the whole way there?
後は　あまり捻りがないのだが
I didn't think too much over the next one but...
「ただし　その頃にはあんたは八つ裂きになっているだろうけどな」と
"However, by that point you'll have been torn into pieces."
これぐらいか
Something like that?
Ah, whatever, that's fine!
ああもう　それでいい　それで行こう
Let's go with that.
I said that's fine.
それがいいと言ったんだ
「ただし　その頃にはあんたは八つ裂きになっているだろうけどな」
"However, by that point you'll have been torn into pieces."
うん　とてもいい感じだ
Yes, it sounds good.
ああ　これでいいのか
You're okay with this?
I didn't expect that.
少し意外だな
これは考えた中ではそれほど強く推すつもりのない一品だったのだが
It's not a choice I was expecting to really push while I was thinking it up.
まあ　そうは言っても自信作であったことには違いがない
Though that said, it's certainly a work I'm proud of.
Yeah, I'm totally shocked.
ああ　びっくりしたぜ
俺に似合いすぎる
It matches me so well!
I see, I see.
そうかそうか
これはそなたの超必殺技であるところの
This idea was born from your super ultimate "Shichika Hachiretsu" move.
「七花八裂」から着想得たものなのだ
I-I see.
そ　そうか
Yep, you can go ahead and thank me.
うむ　礼を言っていいぞ
感謝感激雨あられ
You made my day.
Indeed, I see, I see.
うむうむ　そうかそうか
そなたが気に入ったのならば是非はない
Well if you like it then that's that.
しかし　そなたの好みが煩いせいで
Though because you were so picky, this discussion went on longer than I thought it would.
思いのほか長話になってしまったな
とはいえ　まだ急がなければならぬほどではない
That said, not so long that we have to rush or anything.
この調子なら　夕方ごろには目的地に着くであろう
At this pace, we'll reach our destination around evening.
あ　ただしその頃にはあんたは八つ裂きになっているだろうけどな
Yeah...
However, by that point you'll have been torn into pieces.
「チェリオ」
Cheerio!!
そなた何も考えておらんなあ
Do you not think?!
ややこしいな
You're so confusing...
ああ　ちなみに先から多用している「チェリオ」だが
Incidentally, that "cheerio!" I've been using is my catchphrase.
これは私の口癖だ
I-I see... I didn't really notice...
そ　そうか
気にもしていなかった
「チェリオ」とは九州のな
"Cheerio" is a popular phrase in the Satsuma domain in Kyushu.
薩摩藩あたりで流行している気合を入れるための掛け声だ
これは方言と言うより　むしろ文化かな
It's not so much in the dialect, but more like part of the culture.
別に私は九州とゆかりがあるというわけではないのだが
I don't have any particular connection to Kyushu, but the expression "cheerio" just seems kind of cute to me.
「チェリオ」なんて気合を入れる掛け声の割に
なんだか発音が可愛いであろう
これは私の外見感の相乗効果もあって
I'm actually quite proud of the effect it has when combined with my appearance.
かなり期待できる思いつきだと自負しておる
報告書を提出した後には
I'm sure it'll catch on once I submit my report to the Shogunate.
もちろん　ご存知のとおり
Of course, as you are aware,
薩摩藩が発祥の気合を入れるための掛け声は「チェスト」
the phrase originating from the Satsuma domain used to raise one's spirits is "chesuto".
The expression "cheerio" which Togame uses is a foreign word meaning "goodbye".
とがめの言う「チェリオ」では
「別れ」を意味する外来語となってしまいます
彼女がその間違いに気付き
The story of when she notices her mistake and loses herself with embarrassment is yet some months away.
恥ずかしさのあまり稀な混乱ぶりを見せてしまうことになるのは
これより数ヵ月後の物語でございます
Hakuhei!
白兵　その刀貰い受ける
I'll be taking that sword!
御主もまた刀の魔力に取り付かれた迷い人でござるか
You too, have become lost to this sword's magic?
Here I come!
参ら
拙者にときめいてもらうでござる
I'll have you fall for me.
か　格好いい
S-So cool...
待って待って　歩くのが早いぞ
Wait up, you're walking too fast!
Ah, sorry.
ああ　悪い　人と歩くのは慣れてないからな
I'm not used to walking with anyone.
あんた着込んでるから足が重いんだよ
You're heavy because you're wearing too much.
Fool!
たわけ　女子に軽々しく重いとか言うな
Don't frivolously call a lady heavy!
いや　あんたは十分軽いって
Well you're definitely light,
けど　そんな格好じゃ動きづらいだろう
but isn't it hard to move with all that?
Once again, you're an idiot.
重ねてたわけ
女子のお洒落は別筋肉だ
Women use different muscles to stay fashionable.
女子にはそんな器官があるのか
Women have such body parts?
Parts that a backwater barbarian like you wouldn't understand.
粗野な男には分からぬ繊細な器官よ
Well, I don't care about fashion or whatever.
まあ　お洒落なんてどうでもいいけどよ
Clothes just get in the way when you wear them.
服なんて着るだけ邪魔だと思うけどな
そなたの上半身に服を着せることを私はすでに諦めているが
I've already given up on trying to get you to clothe your upper body.
下半身までは脱いでくれるなよ
Just don't take off anything from your lower half, please.
変態と旅はしたくない
I don't want to travel with a pervert.
安心しろ
Don't worry.
あんたが買ってくれたこの袴はそこそこ気に入っている
I've taken a liking to this hakama that you bought me.
動きやすいし　戦いやすい
It's easy to move and easy to fight in.
Ease of movement and ease of fighting are different?
動きやすいと戦いやすいは違うのか
Yeah they're different.
まあ　違うね
で　その下酷城はまだなのか
So is there still a ways to go till we get to Gekoku Castle?
夜になっちまうぞ
It'll be night soon, and that'd be inconvenient for you, right?
そうしたら困るのはとがめだろう
Indeed.
そうだな　女子が砂漠で露宿とあっては
Letting a girl sleep outdoors in the desert would be a total waste of her fashion.
せっかくのお洒落が台無しだ
Is that the problem here?
そういう問題か
誰だ こんなところにものを置いた奴は
Who the hell left this here?!
こいつは真庭にの真庭白鷺
This is Maniwani's... Maniwa Shirasagi!
へえ 城 なんで
The castle?
How...
蜃気楼により大気の迷彩
It's a camouflage caused by a mirage in the air.
ここまで近寄らねば認識できない
You can't see it till you get this close.
それが因幡砂漠の下酷城だ
That's the Inaba desert's Gekoku castle.
攻めるに固く　守るに易い
Strong offense, easy to defend.
知らない人間は知らないことだが
Most people don't know about it, but it's famous among certain groups.
一部では有名な話ではある
That was quite a shock!
びっくりしちまったじゃねえか
すまぬ　そなたをびっくりさせようと思って
Sorry.
I thought I'd try surprising you.
So why is his body discarded like this outside the castle?
そいつ　城のそばに捨てられていたってことは
Apparently the 12 Maniwa corps leaders are competing.
真庭忍軍は十二頭領内で競争しておるといっておったが
四季崎記紀の完成形変体刀　十二本収集競争
It's a race to collect Shikizaki Kiki's 12 perfected Deviant Blades.
おそらくは因幡下酷城の宇練銀閣が斬刀　鈍を所有していると知り
Presumably, Shirasagi learned that Uneri Ginkaku of Gekoku castle holds Zantou Namakura, and came to take it.
白鷺はここを訪れたのであろう
そして　返り討ちにあった
And then got cut down instead...
真庭忍軍の頭領がこのざまとは
To think a Maniwa corps head was brought down like this...
I've beaten a Maniwani head too, you know.
真庭にの頭領なら俺も倒したぜ
In your case, you were merely blessed with luck.
そなたの場合は運にも恵まれていただろうが
まあ　前向きに考えるとしよう
Let's think of it positively...
先にたどり着いた真庭にが斬刀の収集に失敗した
The Maniwani who got here first failed to get Zantou.
これは捕らえようによっては悪いことでもあるまい
Depending on your perspective, that could be a good thing.
もしも白鷺が変体刀収集に成功していれば
If Shirasagi had succeeded in obtaining the Deviant Blade, we'd have come here for nothing.
無駄足になってしまっておったのだからな
I see, that is positive.
なるほど　前向きだ
But because of this guy's failed attempt, the castle lord will be on his guard now.
だけど　こいつが襲撃に失敗したことで
ここの城主は警戒しちまっただろう
Worst case, he might even have run away.
最悪の場合姿を消しているかもしれないぜ
それはない
He won't have.
宇練銀閣は因幡全土が砂漠化しても
Uneri Ginkaku is the man who didn't leave this land even after the entirety of Inaba turned to desert.
それでもこの土地から退かなかった男だ
それに　この白鷺の有様を見る限り
Furthermore, by the looks of Shirasagi here,
Uneri has complete faith in his own skills.
宇練は自分の腕に絶対の自信を持っておる
士道不覚悟の敵前逃亡など考えもすまい
Fleeing before an approaching foe wouldn't even cross his mind.
どうやら思っていた以上に強敵のようだな
It seems he's a stronger opponent than we thought, huh.
あるいは出直すってのもありかもしれねえぜ
We could also come back later, you know?
ありえん話だ
Not a chance.
真庭忍軍がこれほどの速度で動いている今
We can't afford to waste any time now that the Maniwa corps are moving so fast.
私がたたらを踏んでいる暇などあるものか
七花　私は今むしろ安心しているところなのだ
Quite the opposite Shichika, I'm glad this happened.
真庭白鷺が引き立て役になってくれたおかげで
I've got something interesting to write in my report now, thanks to Maniwa Shirasagi giving us this opportunity.
上に提出する報告書に盛り上がりができたのだからな
裏切り者の真庭忍軍
To be able to report that we took the Deviant Blade from the swordsman who cut down Maniwa Shirasagi the traitor...
それを撃退したという剣士から変体刀を収集したなだと
How satisfying!
なんとも痛快ではないか
何より
And most importantly, now I don't have to write down any tedious backwards talking.
「逆さ喋り」などという描写のうっとうしい忍者を
これで私は書かずに済む
S-Sure...
And anyway, are you suggesting I write about us turning tail even though we're so well prepared?
大体　七花
ここまでお膳立てが整っていながら
すごすご引き下がるなどと言う格好悪い有様を
そなたは私に書けというのか
I see, that certainly is positive.
なるほど　前向きだ
Yep.
だから　俺はあんたに惚れたんだ
This is why I fell for you.
前に出ると危ないじゃないか
Isn't it dangerous for you to go first?
戦うのは俺なんだろう
I'm the one fighting, right?
Or do you plan to take on Uneri Ginkaku yourself first?
それともあんたがまず最初に宇練銀閣と戦おうってのか
馬鹿者　私の戦闘力はそなたもよく知るところだろう
Idiot.
You know very well how good I am at fighting.
I'd be easier for him to defeat me than to rip a paper screen.
私を倒すことなど　障子紙を破くよりも容易いぞ
Even if you say that so proudly...
そんなこと威張って言われても
Look, apparently you're misunderstanding this part of the process, so I'll make it clear.
あのな
どうもそなたはその辺りを誤解しているようだから一応言っておくが
We didn't come here as thieves.
私たちは別に強盗というわけではないのだ
We can't just run in, swords swinging, and pillage it.
いきなり丁々発止のちゃんばらを行い
強奪すれば良いというものではない
手順を踏み　交渉が必要なのだよ
We have to follow proper procedures and negotiate.
Um... "procedures", like at a government office?
ええと　お役所的な手続きってことか
Let's say that's how it is for now.
今回のところはその理解でもいい
If that's all it takes, you don't really need me do you?
それで済むんだったら
別に俺要らないんじゃないのか
四季崎の刀の毒を好んで摂取するような人間は
It's almost a certainty that anyone who would consume the poison of Shikizaki's swords is insane.
凡そ狂人と相場は決まっておるでな
つまり端から交渉で済むと思ってないってことだろう
So basically, you're not expecting that negotiation can settle this to begin with.
But even so...
しかしな そうは言ってもだ
I need to consider the chance that it can.
例えば　刀の所有者が善人だった時
Take for example the case where the sword owner happens to be a good person.
What would you do then?
そなたはどうするつもりなのだ
As long as we have the backing of the Shogunate, we won't be punished even if we do kill people.
幕府の後ろ盾がある以上  人を斬っても咎められることはないが
だからと言って無闇やだらに切り刻んで良いということではないのだ
But that doesn't make it okay to senselessly cut people up.
分かったら行くぞ
Now that's out the way, let's go.
明白に怪しい襖だが
This is a suspiciously obvious screen...
ここに何かあるってことだろう
which means there's something here, right?
あぁ待て　無用心に開けるな　こら
Wait, don't just open it!
おい
Hey!
You must be Uneri Ginkaku.
宇練銀閣だな
I'm the army general director in support of critical tasks under direct control of Yanari Shogun of the Owari Shogunate,
私は尾張幕府家鳴将軍家直轄　預奉所軍所総監督
Togame the Strategian.
奇策士とがめだ
その刀
That sword appears to be Zantou Namakura.
斬刀 鈍と見受けるが  如何かな
Am I correct?
うるせえな
What a racket.
確かに俺は宇練銀閣だが
It's true I am Uneri Ginkaku.
You don't have to shout like that.
そう大きな声で怒鳴るなよ
Pardon me.
それは失礼した
So?
幕府のお偉いさんがこんな砂漠に何の用だよ
Why is a big shot from the Shogunate here in the desert?
Would you consider handing over Zantou?
その斬刀
譲ってもらえんかな
もちろんただとは言わん
Of course, I'm prepared to pay.
I'll provide anything the shogunate can offer.
幕府としてできる限りのことはさせてもらおう
You know, just a bit earlier some fake-looking ninja came along and said something similar.
この前よ
忍者の偽者みたいな奴が来て
あんたと似たようなことを言ってたけど
What's with that?
何あれ　あんたらの友達
A friend of yours?
He's no friend of ours.
友達ではない
私たちはあんな下種な忍者とは違う
We're different from that ninja scum.
We want to make a fair trade.
正当な取引を望む者だ
Of course, even given that it's a single sword, I'm well aware of its value.
無論　刀一本とは言え
そなたの差すその刀の価値は　よく認識しておるつもりだ
I understand that it's not something you can just replace.
間違っても 他の何かに換えられるものではあるまい
しかし宇練よ そこを曲げて　幕府のために
However, I'd like you to consider this offer for the sake of the Shogunate — no, for the whole world.
ひいては天下国家のために貢献してはくれぬか
There isn't a single sane person who talks about a unified country these days.
天下国家のためになんて奴に　碌な奴はいねーよ
Indeed.
ああ　お主だって
I'm sure you don't wish to continue living aimlessly in the desert like this.
いつまでもこの城の中でのうのうと暮らしておるつもりはないであろう
野心があるのならば
If you have any ambitions, I can assist you.
私は協力できると思うぞ　表にも　裏にもだ
Both in public and in the shadows.
Are you saying you'd support a ronin like myself?
浪人の俺を取り立ててくれるってのかい
ありがたい話だがね
I'm grateful for the offer, but I've heard there's a bounty on my head.
しかし俺の首には賞金がかかってるとも聞くぜ
Of course, I can release you from that burden.
無論　その枷も外してやれる
どんな望みも思うがままだ
You can have anything you desire.
Hey, Uneri!
おい　宇練
I couldn't quite hear you properly this time.
今度は声が小さすぎてよく聞こえねえな
Could you come a bit closer?
もうちょっと近付いてきてくれねえか
大体　敷居越しに話をするなんて
Besides, isn't it rude to speak to a swordsman from across a door?
剣士に対して失礼だろうがよ
I don't know exactly how important you are,
あんたがどれだけ偉いか知らねえけど
少なくともそれは頼み事をしようって態度じゃねえよな
but that isn't the right attitude for someone asking a favor.
確かにそのとおりだ
You're quite right.
失礼した
Excuse me.
Kyotouryuu: Lily!
虚刀流 「百合」
What are you doing?!
何すんじゃー
Calm down.
落ち着けよ
You think I can calm down after suddenly being kicked, you idiot?!
いきなり蹴られて落ち着けるか　この馬鹿者
A mysterious force suddenly pulling me backwards...
後から見えない力に吸い寄せられるから
I thought aliens were abducting me!
宇宙人に誘拐されたかと思ったわ
You certainly have quite the imagination...
その発想は物凄いが
So that was Iainuki...
Note: Kneeling sword draw
居合い抜きか
If I hadn't been wearing as much clothing, I'd be...
も　もしも厚着をしていなければ
今頃私の体は
I'm pretty sure it'd be the same either ways.
いや　その分だけの着物が無事で済んだだけだと思うけど
びっくりした
I'm shocked.
この斬刀を手にして以来
This is the first time my Zerosen has been evaded since I inherited Zantou.
俺の零閃が躱されたのは初めてだぜ
I'm the one who's shocked.
びっくりしたのはこっちのほうだ
居合い抜きが剣術の究極形というのは聞いていたが
I'd heard Iainuki was a supreme sword technique, but to think it's that fast...
そこまで速いものだとは
So with my shock and your shock, we're even.
んじゃまぁ お前のびっくりと俺のびっくりでおあいこってことで
Uneri!
宇練 貴様今自分が何をしたのか分かっておるのか
Do you understand what you've just done?
The same goes for you too, bringing along such a skilled big brother.
あんたもさそんな腕の立つお兄ちゃん連れてきているくらいなんだ
最終的には腕っ節に訴えてくるつもりがあったんだろう
You intended to do things by force from the start, right?
Big brother?!
お兄ちゃんだと
Do I look like this guy's little sister??
貴様　私がこいつの妹に見えるのか
What part of me looks like a "little sister"?!
私のどこが妹だ
My ancestors refused to give up this sword to their own masters, let alone the Shogunate.
俺のご先祖様はよ
主君も どころか当時の将軍すら敵に回しても
この刀を譲らなかったんだってよ
If I simply said "here you go" and gave it up to you, I'd be the laughing stock of my dead fathers.
なのに俺が「はい そうですか」とあんたにこれを渡したんじゃ
草葉の陰で笑い物だぜ
Are you afraid of losing that sword?
その刀を無くすのが怖いのか
その零閃って技
You can't reach that level of speed with that Zerosen move of yours without it, right?
そいつじゃなけりゃそこまでの速度は出ないんだろ
So are you afraid of losing it?
だからそれを失うのが怖いのか
And what if I am?
怖かったら何だ
That's fine.
別に
それが刀を使う剣士の限界なんだろうなと思ってさ
I was just thinking to myself that that must be the limit for sword users.
そういうお前は剣士じゃねえのか
Aren't you a swordsman yourself?
I am most definitely a swordsman.
剣士だよ　紛うことなくな
ええ　だったら　剣士に言葉は不要なんだよ
In which case, no further words are needed, as swordsmen.
If you want this sword, stop talking and come get it.
この刀が欲しいってんなら黙って奪い取ればいい
And I'll stop talking and fight back.
俺はそれに　黙って抵抗するだけだ
ああ　意地か
Stubbornness?
It's pride.
気位だよ
You may be confident after saving that woman,
お前はその女を庇えていい気になってんのかもしれねえが
but that wasn't my full strength just now.
今のが全力だと思うなよ
零閃の最高速度が
Zerosen at full speed is faster than light.
光を超える
やるか
Want to do this?
Togame.
とがめ
確認したいことができたんだけど
I want to confirm something.
いいか
Is that okay?
Hey...
おい
Just a bit of strategizing.
ちょっと作戦会議だ
We'll be back soon, so take a nap or something.
すぐに戻ってくるから
転寝でもして待ってろ
その時は披露してもらうぜ
When I'm back, I'll have you show me your full speed Zerosen or whatever.
最高速度の零閃とやらをよ
Close the screen on your way out.
襖　閉めて行けよ
Oh yeah...
ああ　そうだ
You didn't tell me your name yet, big brother.
まだお兄ちゃんの名前は聞いてなかったな　教えとけよ
虚刀流七代目当主　ヤシュリ七花だ
I'm the 7th Kyotouryuu head...
Yashuri Shichika.
My tongue slipped...
噛んじゃった
Don't look so upset.
そう不機嫌そうな顔すんなよ
ああしなちゃ　あんら真っ二つだったんだぜ
If I hadn't done that you'd be in two pieces!
I don't look upset, 'kay!
不機嫌そうな顔などしておらんもん
"'kay"?
もん
Uh... I mean...
あいや　不機嫌そうな顔などしておらんわ
I don't look upset!
You're ridiculously childish sometimes...
偶にあんたすげえ子供っぱいこと言うけどさ
How old are you, anyway?
正確にはあんた何歳なんだ　俺より年上なんだよな
You are older than me, right?
That's irrelevant.
そんなことはどうでも良かろう
それより七花
More importantly Shichika, what did you want to confirm?
確認したいことは何だ
あそこで戦闘を中断する理由があったとは　私には思えないのだが
I can't see a good reason for you to have stopped the fight at that point.
あいつがそれに応じるかどうかを確認したかったんだ
I wanted to see if he'd let us.
If he'd let us?
応じるかどうか
つまりあの場から立ち去る俺ととがめをあいつが追って来るかどうか
Basically, whether he'd chase us or not as we left.
けれどあいつはそうしなかった
But he let us go.
Well, that's true...
まあ　そうだが
The moment you crossed the boundary into that room, he attacked you.
とがめが敷居を跨いであの部屋に入った瞬間に
あいつは斬り付けてきた
Looking at it the other way, he won't attack us as long as we don't enter that room.
逆に言えば あの部屋に入らない限り
あいつは俺たちを攻撃してこないということだ
あの奥まった部屋こそが
That secluded room is optimal for him to ambush his foes.
敵を迎撃する上で都合がいいんだ
I see.
なるほど
That's why Maniwa Shirasagi had no choice but to face him up front.
真庭白鷺も正面から勝負せざるを得なかったわけか
That room is Uneri Ginkaku's absolute territory.
あの部屋は完全に宇練銀閣の領域だ
では　あいつを部屋から引きずり出せば良いのだろうが
Then we should find a way to drag him out of that room.
Do you have a plan?
そなた考えがあるのか
First, you'll enter the room.
まず　とがめがあの部屋に入る
ふむふむ　私が入ると
Okay, I'll enter...
Then, falling prey to Zerosen, you get cut in two.
そして　零閃の餌食となって真っ二つになる
I see.
Since he can't just abandon your corpse,
死体を傍に放置しておくわけにもいくまい
he'll have to leave the castle to dispose of you, like with Maniwa Shirasagi.
真庭白鷺の例と同じく
城外へと捨てるはずなんだ
And then?
そしてそして
Then I get him.
そこを俺が討つんだよ
Cheerio!
ちぇりお
I have to get cut in two for that!
私が真っ二つになってしまっておるだろうが
That's why I was thinking it might not work.
うん　だからこの案は使えないかなぁと思っている
Of course not!
当然だ
Well, even if we give up on luring him out, I still have a plan, Togame.
だから　誘き出すのは諦めるとして
それでもなお　対策はあるんだよ とがめ
Do I get split into two in this plan?
その対策とやらでは 私は真っ二つにはならんのだろうな
If you have to face your opponent directly, just do it.
まともに勝負せざるを得ない相手なら
まともに勝負をすればいい
Shichika,
七花 それが結論だったら私は怒るぞ
if that's the conclusion you came to, I'm going to be angry.
No, you've been angry the whole time.
いや　あんた最初からずっと怒ってるよ
茶かすな
Don't mock me!
You know,
なぁ　今日だけじゃなく
I think just winning today isn't good enough to win tomorrow's battles.
あしたも勝つためには　ただ勝つんじゃ駄目だと思う
蝙蝠の時みたいに　好運に恵まれて勝つんじゃ駄目なんだ
We can't just win by luck like with Koumori.
That's unexpectedly serious, coming from you.
思いの外真面目なことを言う
I have to protect the swords, as well as you, right?
「刀を守れ」そして「あんたを守れ」だろう
そ　それが分かっているのなら
I-If you understand that then stop coming up with plans that involve splitting me in half!
私が真っ二つになるような案をそもそも思いつきすらするでない
And so, I'll ask that you stand behind me.
そこでだ　あんたは俺の後ろにいてくれ
As insurance, just in case.
いざって時の保険だよ
I'm sure you're already aware, but I have no skills by which to cover your back.
分かっているとは思うけれど
私にそなたの背中を守れるような才覚はないぞ
That's not what I mean.
そんなんじゃねえよ
Shichika...
七花
How can I put it...
なんて言うか
この場で上手く言うことはできないんだけどな
I can't express it very well, but I want you to do this.
あんたには　そうして欲しいんだよ
要するに
Basically, people with something to protect are strong.
守るものがある奴は強いってことだ
He said Kyotouryuu...
虚刀流と言ったか
A martial art based on swordsmanship?
剣術を雛形にした拳法
A swordsman gains nothing by discarding his sword.
剣士が剣を捨てることに利点はない
What a creepy style.
何とも不気味な流派じゃねえか
Well whatever.
まあいい
There's no use thinking about it.
考えても詮無きことだ
俺はこの城と刀を守るだけ
I need only protect this castle and this sword.
That's all.
それだけだ
誰もが挙ってこの砂漠から逃げ出した
Everyone ran from the desert, abandoning their homeland.
みんな故郷を捨てた
Perhaps, if I wasn't the last one,
或いは　最後の一人でなければ
I'd have been able to leave Inaba too.
俺も因幡を去れたかもしれない
No, leaving was never an option.
いや 俺には端からその選択はなかった
I am not allowed to be indecisive.
迷うことは許されない
Is this my anchor to this land, to this sword?
この地への この刀への偏執か
It truly is an obsession.
そしてそれは　妄執だ
A swordsman needs something to protect.
剣士には守るものが必要だ
Without that, he cannot fight.
そうでなければ　戦えなくなる
Yo.
よう
Sorry for the wait.
待たせたな
Indeed.
So?
それでお兄ちゃん　俺の零閃対策でも考えてきたのか
Did you come up with a counter to my Zerosen?
うーん　微妙なところだな
In a way.
What, Kyotouryuu even has a counter for Iainuki?
何だ
虚刀流には居合い抜き対策でもあるってのかい
うん まあ　相手があんたほどの手合いなら
Well, if the opponent is someone at your level, it'll probably work.
たぶん成功すると思う
For this technique, the faster the opponent's sword moves, the more effective it becomes.
この技は相手の剣が速ければ速いほど 成功率が跳ね上がるからよ
Kyotouryuu, 7th stance: Iris.
虚刀流七の構え「杜若」
What's with that ridiculously obvious pose?
何だその明かな突撃の構えは
I thought he had a counter, but that's it?
対策があるみたいな口振りでそれか
It appears I'm not being taken seriously.
甘く見られたもんだ　虚刀流
Kyotouryuu...
clearly not a worthy opponent.
相手にとって満足無しか
Idiot, he's just taunting you!
アホ　馬鹿にされているんだ
Well whatever.
まあ　いいや
All right then, on your marks...
それじゃまあ　位置について 用意
Get set...
Go!
どん
The distance is three steps!
前は三歩
一
One!
Two!
二
Three!
三
零閃
Zerosen!
Kyotouryuu: Rose!
虚刀流 「薔薇」
おう　やったか
You got him?
No, it was too weak!
駄目だ　浅い
っく　足さばきの陽動は認めてやる
I'll admit that was a good feint with your footwork.
I tried to cut at a phantom illusion.
在りもしねえ幻覚を斬っちまった
だがな
But why did you hold back?
何だその爪の甘さはよ
What does he mean?
どういうことだ
Rose would have finished him if I hadn't held back.
「薔薇」は決まっていたんだよ 俺が加減しなければな
His sword pressure caught me off guard.
奴の剣圧にびびっちゃった
Crap!
しくじった　こんな所で実戦経験の少なさが出たか
To have his lack of real battle experience show now of all times...
Shichika!
七花
Don't move!
動くな
Stay behind me!
俺の背中から出るんじゃない
Idiot!
馬鹿者　策の通じなかった今 そんな言葉が聞けるか
You think I can just sit by after your plan failed?
That surprised me...
びっくりした
Now that you've done it twice, I'm sure it isn't dumb luck.
二回続けばもう紛れじゃねえやな
I'm completely awake now, Kyotouryuu.
すっかり目が覚めちまったよ　虚刀流
This is the best I've felt since I was born screaming into this world.
こんなに気分がいいのは　おぎゃあと生まれた時以来だ
You're welcome, and good morning.
そいつはどうも　おはようございます
And good night to you.
そしてお休みなさい
…かな
I'm aware that what you did was extraordinary.
さっきのがとんでもねえ境地だってことぐらいは分かるぜ
But don't think the same thing will work again.
しかし　同じ手が通じると思うなよ
Hurting him was a bad move...
敵を手負いにさせたのはまずかったぞ
Zerosen formation: Five lives!
零閃編隊――五機
Five attacks...
五連撃
With this, it won't matter whether you speed up or slow down.
これなら
お前が多少加速しょうが減速しょうが関係あるまい
I'll easily overcome any small errors like that.
その程度の誤差など　軽く呑み込んでしまう
You were hiding that the whole time?
それがあんたの隠しだまってわけか
This?
これが
No, no, not at all.
いやいや違うね
Wha—
な　何が起きた
What happened?
He cut himself...
自分で自分を斬りやがった
What for?
何のために
これこそ宇練金閣の一万人斬りの秘密だよ　虚刀流
This is the technique Uneri Kinkaku used to kill 10,000 soldiers.
Observe, Kyotouryuu.
見な
When my blood flows into the sheath and soaks the sword,
鞘内を血で濡らし
血を溜め じっとりと湿らせることによって
its draw speed increases.
鞘走りの速度を上げると
The friction between the blade and sheath disappears, and Zerosen reaches the speed of light.
刀と鞘の摩擦係数を格段に落として
零閃は光速へと達する
This is Zantou Namakura's limited hidden art, Zantou Gari!
それが斬刀 鈍限定奥義　斬刀狩り
The more it cuts, the faster it becomes.
斬れば斬るほど速くなるってわけだ
あっ　閃いた
I've got an idea!
七花　今こそ戦術的撤退だ
Shichika, let's make a tactical retreat.
If we just leave him alone he'll bleed to death.
あやつをほうっておくと　出血多量で死ぬぞ
I refuse.
却下だ
It's a chance to win!
正気ではないか
That wouldn't be winning.
そんなの勝利とは言わん
I told you, I won't win by chance.
言っただろう　偶然じゃ駄目だ
かっこいいな　あんた
That's pretty cool of you.
Looking at you, it makes me ashamed that I was hiding moves.
あんたを見ていると　奥の手を隠していた自分が恥ずかしいぜ
No more holding back.
出し惜しみは止めた
I'll show you the full might of Kyotouryuu.
虚刀流の全てを見せて
やろう
Let's go.
ああ　そうだ
Ah, actually there's one thing I want to ask you about.
ちょっと気になったんで訊いときてーんだけどよ　お姉ちゃん
Lil lady, you said that if I handed this Zantou over,
あんた　もしもこの斬刀をあんたに引き渡したら
you'd grant any wish of mine, right?
俺の望みを叶えてくれるって言ったよな
Y-Yeah...
だったら　斬刀を引き渡す代わりに
Then, in exchange for this Zantou, can you restore Inaba to how it was?
この因幡を元通りにしてもらうってのは有りかい
I can't do that.
それは無理だ
The Shogunate has already decided the Tottori domain no longer exists.
既に鳥取蕃は　幕府にとっては存在しない蕃になっておる
And even if they hadn't, there's no way to reverse the desertification.
そうでなくとも
砂漠化した地帯を元通りにする方法など　仮説さえもない
I see.
そうか
Well, I guess that means I wasn't wrong in attacking you.
じゃ　まあ
あんたを斬り付けた俺の判断に　間違いはなかったってことか
That's a relief.
安心したぜ
Why are you doing this?
あんた　なんでこんなことやってんだ
I wonder.
さあね
Is it for that "pride" stuff you were talking about?
さっきも言ってた気位ってやつか
I wonder about that too.
それも　さあね
I just said that on the spot.
あれは適当に言った言葉だよ　本気にすんな
Don't take it seriously.
I just wanted to protect something.
ただ俺も　何かを守りたかっただけだよ
何かを守りたかっただけなのに
But even though I wanted to protect something, this was the only thing left to me to protect.
守るべきもんが　俺にはこれくらいしかなかったんだ
そっか
I see...
Let's go then.
じゃあ　行くぜ
Yeah,
ああ　零閃は何時何時でも出撃可能だ
my Zerosen's ready to go anytime.
Observe Zerosen surpassing the speed of light.
光速を超えた零閃を見るがいい
And if you really have a hidden trick up your sleeve, show me that too.
そして　もしも本当にそんなものがあるのなら
お前も奥の手とやらを見せてみろ
Sure, I'll show you it.
ああ　見せてやる
However, by that point you'll have been torn into pieces.
ただしその頃には
あんたは八つ裂きになっているだろうけどな
On your marks...
位置について　ようい　どん
Get set...
Go!
Zerosen formation: Ten lives!
零閃編隊――十機
ぎゃふんっ
Gyafun!
"Everything is within Zerosen's range"?
全てが零閃の射程範囲内
Wrong!
違うな
You can't draw straight above your head!
真上の敵には居合い抜きもねえだろう
K-Kyotouryuu!
虚刀流
Kyotouryuu seventh hidden art: Rakka Rouzeki!
Note: Scattered Blossoms
虚刀流七の奥義―「落花狼藉」
So where are we going next?
なあ　次はどこへ行くんだ
Hey.
なあ
Hey, Togame!
おい　とがめ
Don't ignore me!
無視すんなよ
You've been like that since yesterday!
昨日からずっとじゃないか
Were you injured somewhere when I kicked you?
ひょっとして俺が蹴った時にどっか怪我でもしたのか
You're so noisy!
喧しいわ　人が怒っているというのに気安く話しかけ続けるな
Stop trying to speak so normally to someone when they're mad at you!
Geez, I'd never have thought you'd use me as a wall to kick off of!
まったく
まさか壁として蹴飛ばす為に後ろに立たされていたとは思わんかったわ
Ah, you're angry at that.
ああ　それを怒ってたんだ
I'm not angry!
怒ってない
I was hoping the initial Iris chaining into Rose would do the job...
最初の「杜若」から「薔薇」への連携が通じてたら
それで良かったんだけどな
I really did just mean to use you as insurance.
本当にとがめはただの保険のつもりだったんだ
Why couldn't you have told me that from the start,
だったら　最初からそう言わんか
instead of saying grandiose things like "people with something to protect are strong" or whatever.
守るものがある奴は強いとかなんとか
変に思わせぶりなことを言いおって
Sorry, that was just random babbling.
すまん　あれは口から出任せだ
Don't babble!
出任せとな
People who have something to protect are strong.
守るものがある者は強い
The fact that that is not a means of becoming strong,
それが　方便ではないこと
and that there are people who need something to protect in order to keep living...
生きるために　守るものを必要とする者がいることを
Shichika learned that from this battle.
七花は今回の戦いを通じて知ったのでした
刀語　今月今宵のお楽しみは　ここまでにございます
The story of Katanagatari on this month and this evening ends here.
That reminds me, you haven't actually seen Zantou's blade yet, have you?
そう言えばそなたは　まだ斬刀の刀身を見ておらんのではないか
おれ
Here.
No, it's okay.
いや　いいわ
In the end, I couldn't follow Ginkaku's Zerosen with my eyes,
あっ　結局俺は　銀閣の零閃を目で捕らえることができなかった
so I don't have the right to.
それならば　それが全てだと思うから
そうか
I see.
Hey, what will happen to Inaba after this?
なあ　これから因幡はどうなる
And Gekoku Castle?
下酷城はどうにもならぬな
Nothing.
どうにもならぬな
最早あそこは　幕府の管轄とも言えない
At this point it's already outside the Shogunate's jurisdiction,
so it'll just rot away and perish.
故に朽ち果てるだけだ
Even so, it'll last for ages to come, far longer than ourselves.
それでも　わたしやそなたよりは　ずっと永く
It might even continue on for a thousand more years, just not as a castle.
ひょっとしたら千年先まで　あそこにあり続けるであろうが
しかし　それはもう城ではない
I see.
そうか
Neither swordsmen or their swords can win against nature, I guess.
剣客も刀も　自然には勝てないということなのかな
That's how it is, in the end.
結局　そういうことになるのか
Seems that way.
なりそうだな
But you know, Togame...
しかしとがめ
Uneri's final line...
宇練の最後の台詞は　かっこよかったな
it was really cool.
It wasn't only cool, it brought out his character.
ただかっこいいんじゃなくて　個性が良く出てたっていうかさ
Is that what you'd call a catchphrase?
ああいうのも　口癖っていうのかい
You're a little off.
少し違うな
あれは散り際の一言だ
That was a line to fall by.
A final message,
死に際の言葉
his last words before death.
末期の言葉だ
You could call it his will.
遺言と言ってもよいかもしれぬ
It's different from a catchphrase in that you only say it once in your whole life.
口癖とは異なり
一生に一度
You're not allowed to say it until you're ready to walk to the path to Hades.
黄泉路に旅立たんとする時にしか口にすることを許されぬ台詞だ
そうか
I see.
Does it bother you?
気になるのか
Certainly, one's final words are even more powerful than a catchphrase.
確かに散り際の一言は　口癖よりも更に効果的な台詞となろう
You only say it once in your lifetime, after all.
一生にたった一度の言葉であるが故にな
However, understand that you, Shichika, are not allowed this one chance.
だがしかし七花
そなたはその一度の機会がそもそも許されておらぬのだからな
You needn't give any thought to your last words.
散り際の一言については　一切考えずとも良い
At last, deep sleep is allowed for me.
これで　やっと　ぐっすり眠れる
utsurona keshiki
This empty landscape
空ろな景色　崩れる
kuzureru sajouna kasou
Collapsing into incinerated ashes
砂上の幻想
hitori egaita masshirona sekai
The bright white world I painted alone
一人描いた　真っ白な世界
全てを失い
subete wo ushinai kooritsuita jikan ni
I lose everything, in frozen time
凍りついた時間に
終わりを告げよう静かに
owari wo tsugeyou shizukani kuuhaku no hate he
Let's end it all, in the dead silence of space
空白の果てへ
itsuka koe wo koroshita
I became mute sometime
いつか声を殺した
kodou ueru you ni nemurenu yoru
My starving pulse keeps my awake
凍えるように　眠れぬ夜
kasoku shiteiku senka wo togisumaseru surudoku
Polishing the accelerating war till it is sharp
加速していく閃光を
研ぎ澄ませる　鋭く
saigoni rokuni shinereba
If I can die honorably
最後に彩りし色は
setsunaku chiru tsui no bigaku
Scattering sorrowfully in beauty
刹那に散る　終の美学
setsunaku chiru tsui no bigaku
Scattering sorrowfully in beauty
azayakani iroasenu hane wo egaite
I draw unfading vivid wings
鮮やかに　色あせぬ花を描いて
"However, by that point you'll have been torn into pieces" huh...
ただしその頃にはあんたは八つ裂きになっているだろうけどな
Although it wasn't high on my list of suggestions,
か 優先順位の低いあんたはあったが
if Shichika says he likes it, that's fine.
七花が気に入ったというのなら然もありなん
With this, that plain Shichika will stand out a bit more.
これで地味な七花も少しは個性が立つというものだ
おっ　さて　私も例の逆喋りに挑戦してみるとしよう
Now then, I'll try out this backwards talking thing.
Strategian the Togame,
だめがしくさきくとんかうそろことさいくうろこてず　はず　だが
Shogunate Owari the of Shogun Yana... critical... the...
Like I can do that!
できるか
Next on Katanagatari: Sentou Tsurugi
Sentou
Tsurugi
次回　刀語　千刀 鎩
Cheerio!